Guide to the Owen Luck, Photographs of Alaska and Haida Gwaii, British Columbia
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Photographs of Alaska and Haida Gwaii, British Columbia
2011-2012
WA Photos Folio 151
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.84
(3 boxes)
Photographs of Alaska and Haida Gwaii (formerly known as the Queen Charlotte Islands), British Columbia, 2011-2012, printed as thirty-three black-and-white gelatin silver prints and five color inkjet prints that chiefly document Haida and Tlingit people, sites, and cultures.
Luck, Owen Craig, 1947-
Owen Luck (born 1947)
Owen Luck is an American photographer known for his photography of Native American and First Nation Canadian life and history.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Owen Luck on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2013.
Scope and Contents
Photographs of Alaska and Haida Gwaii (formerly known as the Queen Charlotte Islands), British Columbia, 2011-2012, printed as thirty-three black-and-white gelatin silver prints and five color inkjet prints that chiefly document Haida and Tlingit people, sites, and cultures.
Images of Haida people and sites in 2011 include the installation of totem poles at Hydaburg, Alaska, and views of Ninstints, a historic Haida village site. Portraits of Haida include Crystal Robinson, Darin Swanson, Mary Swanson, Candace White, and Christian White.
Images of Tlingit people and sites include the installation of totem poles at Kalwock, Alaska, in 2011, and a celebration in Juneau, Alaska, in 2012. Identified Tlingit include members of dance groups including the Heinyaa Khwaan Dance Group led by Jonathan O. Rowan, Jr.
Several images document dance groups including Haida members of the Tluu Xaada Naay (Canoe Peoples House) Dance Group from Massett, British Columbia, and Tsimshian members of the Git-Hoan (People of the Salmon) Native Dance Group from Metlakatla, Alaska.
Signed, numbered, and dated by the photographer on versos of prints. Arranged by the photographer.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Black-and-White Photographs, 11 x 14 Inches (28 x 36 centimeters), 2011. II. Black-and-White Photographs, 16 x 20 Inches (41 x 51 centimeters), 2011. III. Black-and-White Photographs, 20 x 24 Inches (51 x 61 centimeters), 2011. IV. Color Inkjet Prints, 17 x 23 Inches (43 x 60 centimeters), 2011-2012.
Haida Indians -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Tlingit Indians -- Pictorial works; Totem poles -- Alaska -- Hydaburg -- Pictorial works; Totem poles -- Alaska -- Klawock -- Pictorial works; Totem poles -- British Columbia -- Ninstints Site -- Pictorial works; Tsimshian Indians -- Pictorial works; Alaska -- Pictorial works; British Columbia -- Pictorial works; Haida Gwaii (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Hydaburg (Alaska) -- Pictorial works; Klawock (Alaska) -- Pictorial works; Ninstints Site (B.C.) -- Pictorial works; Inkjet prints; Photographic prints; Photographs; Luck, Owen Craig, 1947-; Robinson, Crystal -- Portraits; Rowan, Jonathan O., Jr. -- Portraits; Swanson, Darin -- Portraits; Swanson, Mary -- Portraits; White, Candace -- Portraits; White, Christian, 1962- -- Portraits.
- Black-and-White Photographs, 11 x 14 Inches (28 x 36 centimeters), 2011; Series I
  - Kagani Haida, Hydaburg, Alaska
    - Generations Meet. The Totem Pole Raisings Take Place in Conjunction with Culture Camp where Haida Children Learn about their Culture and Art. The Poles are Carved by a few Haida Carvers., 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    - Children Get Carried to the Pole Park, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    - Women Carry a Totem Pole to the Park for Raising, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 3)
    - Totem Pole Going Up, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    - Higher..., 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 5)
  - Tlingit, Klawock, Alaska
    Scope and Contents
    Context provided by Luck for the subseries: "Jon Rowan a respected Tlingit artist teaches, Tlingit children Tlingit Art, from kindergarten until they complete high school. [The year] 2011 marked the first time in eighty years that totem poles in the Totem Pole Park, weathered and worn, were replaced. Five heraldic monuments were stored away and replaced with five new replica poles carved by Jon Rowan and his apprentices, all students before graduating to go on to college.
    In 2013 five more poles will be erected. Another eighty years will go by before this event is renewed."
    - On a Rainy August Morning the Killer Whale Pole is the First Totem Pole to be Carried from Jon Rowan's Long House for a Rainy Three Miles to the Totem Pole Park in the Heart of Klawock, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 6)
    - The Killer Whale Pole Moves Along..., 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 7)
    - Aided by a Young Tlingit Warrior, Tlingit Men Haul a Second as it Makes its Way to the Park, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 8)
    - Straight into the Afternoon Sun of the Only Day it Did Not Rain. Tlingit Men Heft a Double Flicker Pole to its Raising Place, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 9)
    - It Takes the Effort of Many Hands to Lift the Pole, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 10)
    - A Tlingit Chieftain of the Flicker Clan Looks on as the Pole Celebrating his Clan is Made Fast, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 11)
    - A Tlingit Elder Greets the Photographer, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 12)
    - A Tlingit Family from Ketchikan, Alaska Poses, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 13)
    - Members of Jon Rowan's Dance Group Wearing Tlingit War Regalia Carved by Jon Rowan Gather for a Photograph, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 14)
      Members of the Heinyaa Khwaan dance group.
    - Nonnie Mary Swanson, Matriarch of the Haida People, 2011 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 15)
- Black-and-White Photographs, 16 x 20 Inches (41 x 51 centimeters), 2011; Series II
  Black-and-white photographs are gelatin silver prints.
  - Old Masset, Haida Gwaii
    - Luck's Adoptive Haida Family. From left to right: Crystal Robinson (Mother), Darin Swanson (Uncle), Mary Swanson (Nonnie/Grandmother), 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 16)
    - Mary Swanson, Matriarch of the Yahgu Jaanaas/Laanaas Clan, and Haida People, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 17)
    - Darin Swanson, Chief Ginaawaan of Dadens, of the Yahgu Jaanaas/Laanaas Clan, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 18)
    - Candace and Christian White in Christian's "Tluu Xaada Naay" Long House, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
    - Display of Christian White's Art, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 20)
  - S'gung Gwaii, United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) World Heritage Site
    S'gung Gwaii, also known as SG̱ang Gwaay Llanagaay ("Red Cod Island") or by its English name Ninstints, is a Haida village site and part of the Gwaii Haanas National Park Reserve and Haida Heritage Site on Haida Gwaii on the North Coast of British Columbia, Canada. The site became a United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) World Heritage Site in 1981.
    Context provided by Luck for the subseries with a quote by Michael M. Ames, Director of the Museum of Anthropology at the University of British Columbia in the foreword to George F. MacDonald, Ninstints, Haida World Heritage Site, Museum Note No. 12 (Vancouver: University of British Columbia Press, 1983), iii: "The Kunghit Haida of Ninstints are no more -- they did not survive the onslaught of Western civilization. Their village, now only ruins, has been declared a World Heritage Site in memory of the cultivated society that once flourished there. But Ninstints is more than a celebrated relic; it provides as well a lesson in history and morals."
    - Sailing Along the Gwaii Haanas Coast on the Way to S'gung Gwaii, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 21)
    - House Pit, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 22)
    - Detail Totem Pole, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 23)
    - Pole Detail, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 24)
    - Pole Detail in Foreground, 2011 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 25)
- Black-and-White Photographs, 20 x 24 Inches (51 x 61 centimeters), 2011; Series III
  - S'gung Gwaii, United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) World Heritage Site
    - Beginning Down Footpath, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 26)
    - Looking Back Up the Trail, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 27)
    - House Pit Looking Back at the Trail, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 28)
    - Farther Along, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 29)
    - Looking Back, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 30)
    - From the Beach, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 31)
    - Three More Magnificent Mortuary Poles, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 32)
    - Life Goes On, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 33)
- Color Inkjet Prints, 17 x 23 Inches (43 x 60 centimeters), 2011–2012; Series IV
  - Klawock, Alaska
    - The Tlingit and Their Guests Gather in the Totem Pole Park, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 34)
    - Jon Rowan Leads his Dancers into the Hall for the First of Three Nights of Feasting, Singing, and Dancing, as the Tlingit of Klawock, Alaska, Celebrate the Renewal of Their Culture with the Raising of Five New Poles, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 35)
  - Celebration, Juneau, Alaska
    - Killer Whale Dancer of the Git-Hoan (People of the Salmon) Native Dance Group from Metlakatla, Alaska, 2012 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 36)
    - The Haida "Tluu Xaada Naay" dancers, 2012 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 37)
  - Old Masset, Haida Gwaii
    - Christian White Carving an Argillite Raven Head, 2011 (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 38)